Guide to the Farm Security Administration photographs, 1939-1942 RL.11703
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Farm Security Administration photographs, 1939-1942
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Delano, Jack
Lee, Russell, 1903-1986
Schad, Tennyson
Wolcott, Marion Post, 1910-1990
RL.11703
1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 18 photographic prints 11 x 14 inches
The U.S. Farm Security Administration (FSA) was formed in 1937 as part of social and economic reforms following the Great Depression. Collection comprises 18 color photographs taken from 1939 to 1942 by FSA photographers Jack Delano (8 prints), Russell Lee (7) and Marion Post Wolcott (3). Between 1937 and 1946, FSA/OWI photographers created over 175,000 black-and-white images, and only about 1600 color images using Kodachrome chromogenic film. Subjects in this collection are diverse and include sawmills in Georgia and Maine; a wheat field in Washington State, socializing at a rural fair in Pie Town, New Mexico; tobacco cultivation and a federal housing project in Puerto Rico; and a group of African Americans fishing near a cotton plantation in Mississippi. The prints are sized 10x13 and 11x14 inches, and were created in the 1980s by photograph collector Tennyson Schad using the dye transfer process. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Arranged by photographer, and then by date.
The Farm Security Administration Project
The Farm Security Administration (FSA) was created in 1937 under the Department of Agriculture, as part of the U.S. Federal government "New Deal" recovery programs following the Great Depression. Its main purpose was to minister to the needs of and improve the dire situation of impoverished rural people across the U.S.
In support of this effort, the FSA hired noted photographers and oral history interviewers to promote FSA programs and to document economic and social conditions and natural landscapes of the U.S. and its territories, as well as to illustrate the still-present vitality of the United States in the aftermath of the Depression. Led by economist/photographer Roy Stryker, the project ran until 1942, when the FSA was dissolved and subsumed under the Office of War Information (OWI). Many of the photographers hired for the FSA continued their work under the OWI.
Between 1937 and 1946, FSA/OWI photographers created over 175,000 black-and-white images, and only about 1600 color images using Kodachrome chromogenic film, at that time a relatively new technology. Among the FSA photographers were Jack Delano, Russell Lee, and Marion Post Wolcott, whose color images form this collection.
[Adapted from the Library of Congress FSA/OWI Color Photographs Collection website, accessed March 2019.]
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Farm Security Administration photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018 and 2020.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The color prints in this collection were created in the 1980s from original transparencies, using the dye-transfer method.
Content Description
Collection comprises 18 color photographs taken from 1939 to 1942 by Farm Security Administration (FSA) photographers Jack Delano (8 prints), Russell Lee (7) and Marion Post Wolcott (3). The prints are sized 10 x 13 and 11 x 14 inches, with image sizes ranging from 6 1/2 x 9 3/4 to 10 x 13 inches. They were printed by photograph collector and gallery owner Tennyson Schad in the 1980s from original transparencies in the Library of Congress, using the dye transfer process.
Subjects include industrial settings such as a Pennsylvania steel mill and a sawmills in Georgia and Maine; rural settings such as a wheat field in Washington State and grain elevators in Idaho; and photographs of people, including a group of African Americans fishing near a cotton plantation in Mississippi, and a gathering of white men in a rural Kentucky town. One sequence documents people mingling, saying grace, and serving food at a rural fair in New Mexico. There are several photographs of tobacco cultivation and a federal housing project taken in Puerto Rico, where photographer Jack Delano settled shortly after his FSA assignment.
Together, these rare color images reveal the diverse subject and stylistic choices made by these notable photographers commissioned for the FSA project.
Related Materials
Carl Mydans photographs, 1935-1968 [photographs for FSA, 1935]
Walker Evans photographs, 1935-1936 [photographs for the FSA]
Existence and Location of Originals
Original color film transparencies are located at the Library of Congress, Farm Security Administration/Office of War Information Color Photographs collection.
African Americans -- Mississippi -- Portraits; Documentary Photography -- United States; Industries -- United States -- Photographs; New Deal, 1933-1939; Photographers -- United States; Photography -- United States -- History; Women photographers -- United States; Puerto Rico -- Photographs; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; United States -- Photographs; United States -- Rural conditions; United States -- Social conditions -- 1933-1945; United States -- Social life and customs -- 1918-1945; Color prints (photographs); Dye transfer prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); United States. Farm Security Administration
- Jack Delano Farm Security Administration (FSA) photographs, 1940-1942; 8 photographs 1 folder
  Biographical Note
  Born in the Ukraine in 1914, Delano came to the United States in 1923 when he was five. After graduating from Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts in 1937, Delano worked as a photographer for the Farm Security Administration (FSA) and the Office of War Information (OWI). He was also a well-known music composer. He moved to Puerto Rico in 1946 and lived there until his death in 1997.
  - A starch factory along the Aroostook River, Caribou, Aroostook County, Maine, 1940 October; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0001)
    Scope and Contents
    Printed by Tennyson Schad, circa 1986.
  - Sawmill near Van Buren, Maine, 1940 October; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 3/8 x 9 3/4 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0002)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, 1986.
  - A woman painting a view of the Shenandoah Valley from the Skyline Drive, near an entrance to the Appalachian Trail, Virginia, circa 1940; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0003)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, 1985. Title derived from...
    Title on back of print: "Shenandoah Valley, VA." Alternate title on label affixed to sleeve: "Man painting from Skyline Drive, Shenandoah Valley, VA."
  - Tobacco country, vicinity of Barranquitas, Puerto Rico, 1941 December; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0004)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, 1983.
  - Near the waterfront, New Bedford, Massachusetts, 1941 January; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 10 x 13 inches (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0005)
  - Steel mills, Midland, Pennsylvania, 1941 February; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 6 1/2 x 9 3/4 inches (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0006)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, March 1986.
  - Sawmill at Greensboro Lumber Co., Greensboro, Georgia, 1941 June; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 10 x 13 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0007)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, 1985.
  - Federal housing project on the outskirts of the town Yuaco, Puerto Rico. About an acre of land for gardens is provided with each house, 1942 January; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0008)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, 1983. Title and date derived from.... Alternate title on print verso, "Federal housing project, Yuaco, Puerto Rico."
- Russell Lee Farm Security Administration (FSA) photographs, 1940-1941; 7 photographs
  Russell Lee (1903-1990) was born in Illinois. A journalist and photographer, he was best known for his photographic work for the Farm Security Administration from 1936 to 1943. He died in Austin, Texas, where he had taught photography at the University of Texas.
  - Before the barbeque was served at the Pie Town, New Mexico Fair, grace was said, 1940 October; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 10 x 13 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0009)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, 1984 or 1985.
  - Cutting the pies and cakes, Pie Town, New Mexico Fair, 1940 October; Dye tranfer print. Sheet size: 10 x 13 inches; image size: 6 3/4 x 10 1/8 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0010)
  - Friends at the Pie Town, New Mexico Fair, 1940 October; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 10 x 13 inches; image size: 6 5/8 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0011)
  - Mrs. Bill Stagg with state quilt which she made, Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 October; Dye tranfer print. Sheet size: 10 5/8 x 9 3/4 inches; image size: 10 1/8 x 6 3/4 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0012)
  - Saying grace before the barbeque dinner at the Pie Town, New Mexico Fair, 1940 October; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 6 1/2 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0013)
    Print date: 1985
  - Grain elevators, Caldwell, Idaho, 1941 July; RL.11703-P-0008; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0014)
  - Wheat farm, Walla Walla, Washington, 1941 July; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0015)
- Marion Post Wolcott Farm Security Administration (FSA) photographs, 1939-1940; 3 photographs
  - Negroes fishing in creek near cotton plantations outside Belzoni, Mississippi Delta [image 1], 1939 October; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0016)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, 1986. Another print in this series with the same title is from a different frame.
  - Negroes fishing in creek near cotton plantations outside Belzoni, Mississippi Delta [image 2], 1939 October; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 10 x 13 inches; image size: 7 x 10 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0017)
    Credit and copyright stamps on the verso, with inscriptions in pencil by an unknown hand. Printed and signed by Tennyson Schad, December 1986.
    Another print in this series with the same title is from a different frame.
  - Farmers and townspeople in town on court day, Compton, Kentucky, 1940 September; Dye transfer print. Sheet size: 10 x 13 inches; image size: 7 1/4 x 10 1/4 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11703-P-0018)